in this lesson we'll cover a second big use case of open AI functions tool usage in this lesson
we'll first introduce the link chain concept of a tool and then we'll go over how to use open AI
functions to choose which tool to use and then execute that let's dive in when we think about
having a language model use functions there's actually two components to it the first is having
the language model decide which function to use and what the inputs to that function should be
the next component is actually calling that function with those inputs langchain combines
those two ideas into something called a tool which is basically a schema definition for the function
which we can then convert into the open AI function spec and a callable so we can actually call that
model as well we have many of these tools built into the package search tools math tools sql tools
but in this lab we'll largely focus on creating our own tools one thing that we've noticed is that
when you create your own chains and agents a lot of it relies on actually creating your own tools
because what you're trying to do is probably pretty specific to your particular task so we're going
to go over how to create our own tools easily and then we're going to go over how to use a language
model to select which tools to use and then also call those tools let's jump into the code and see what
it looks like we're going to get started with the usual setup and then we're going to import a tool
decorator from LinkedIn so this decorator we can use to put on top of the function
and then when we define the function
so this tool decorator we can put on top of the function that we define what this does is it then
automatically converts this function into a link chain tool that we can use down the line so this
search thing now has a name it now has a description and it now has arguments and so all of these will
be used when creating the open ai functions definition we can also improve upon this by defining a more
explicit structure for the input schema this is often important because again the description of the input
is what the language model uses to determine what the input should be and so having a really clear
definition for the input becomes important we can do this by defining a pydantic model and then when
we define the function we can add in our schema equals search input so search input is this class that
we created up here it's got the same structure as the function so it's got a query parameter which
matches the query parameter there the main difference here is that we're adding a description for that
query parameter and so this is a way of passing descriptions and other information should we want
to include that in the field to the args schema of the tool and so now if we run this and now if we do
and now if we do search.args we can see that we get the description of what we passed in
and again this is still callable so if we do this and we pass in a string we get back the value and
this isn't actually doing anything under the hood but we'll see later on how you can actually do
stuff the first real tool that we're going to create is a tool that gets the current temperature
given a latitude and longitude so first we're going to define the input schema so latitude longitude
and we're going to give it a description we'll then define this function we'll we'll decorate it with
this tool decorator and we'll pass in arg schema equals openmedio input and openmedio is the api
that we're going to use under the hood so we're calling api.openmedio.com we're calling the forecast
endpoint so we're getting a forecast and we're getting one forecast day ahead we're passing in the
longitude and latitude and these are passed into the function we're specifying temperature as what we want to
to get back we're then making this call with the requests library we're then parsing out the response
into json then what we're doing is we're getting the forecast for the next day and we're finding the
point in the forecast that is most close to the current time once we do that and we have that
temperature we're going to respond with the current temperature is blank degrees celsius
if we look at the name and description for this we call it get current temperature if we look at the
description we can see that the description has the signature in there as well as the doc string
and then if we look at the args we can see that it has longitude and latitude
what we can also do is we can convert this tool into the exact open ai functions definition and you can do
this by doing from link chain dot tools dot render import format tool to open ai function and so when we
call this on a given tool
we get back a json blob which combines all those elements and now have the name the description
and then the parameters which include the properties of the longitude and latitude and this is the format
that open ai functions expects and again this tool is callable so if we pass in latitude and longitude
there this is now making a real request to the open media api and getting back a response
the second tool that we're going to define is a wikipedia tool so this is going to search things in
wikipedia so it's going to take in a query and it's first going to call the wikipedia python library dot
search and it's going to get back a list of pages it's going to iterate through the first three elements
in that list and it's going to get more information about that page so it's going to call wikipedia dot
page with the page title that we got back and it's going to get this wiki page element what we're
then going to do is we're going to construct a list of summaries so we're going to put page in the page title
and then summary and the summary of the page and we're going to create that list and then what we're going to respond with is just a
concatenated list of those summaries so if we take a look at this tool we can look at the name we can look at the
description we can convert it to an opai functions definition and then we can also call it with a given query
so let's look up laying chain see what wikipedia knows about laying chain and it returns a bunch of
things the first page that returns is the laying chain page so it's got the page in the summary
if we look down we can see that the next page that returns is about prompt engineering in general
and then the third page that it returns is about sentence embeddings so it's returned three different
things in this large-ish text blob so far what we've done is we've created functions in our notebook and
and then created open ai function definitions for those functions oftentimes functions that we want to
interact with are exposed behind apis and oftentimes apis have a specific specification for their inputs
and outputs called an open api specification and so what we're going to show now is we're going to show
how you can take one of these open api specs and convert it into a list of opening ai function calls and
and again this is really useful because a lot of functionality is behind apis and so having a
general easy way to interact with those apis is going to prove very useful so we're going to import two
things first we're going to import a function called open api spec to open ai function and this is going to
take in an open api spec and can and return a list of open ai functions and then we're also have
and then we also have this open api spec class and this is going to be used to load the open api spec
in the first place let's take a look at this example open api spec we can see that there's a few paths
defined first we have the pets path and there's a get endpoint and this lists all pets we can then see
that there is a post endpoint for the same path and this creates a pet and finally we can see that there's
another endpoint which takes in a pet id and then it gets information for that specific pet
we're going to load the open api spec from this text and we're then going to pass that spec into the
open api spec to open ai function and we're going to get back two things first we're going to get back
the function definitions the open ai function definitions that we can use and then second we'll
also get back a set of callables that we could actually call to invoke those functions because
this is a made-up spec those callables aren't actually going to be real but if this was a real
functioning spec those would work if we take a look at what's in this list we can see that we have
three functions we first have the list pets function then we have the create pets function and then we have the show pet by id function
we'll now show how we can use a language model to determine which of these functions to call
so we're going to import our open ai model
and we're then going to create a simple version of this model and we're going to pass in temperature
equals zero again because when we're choosing between functions we probably want to do that in a pretty
deterministic way and then we're also going to bind in the functions argument to this
we can now try this out on a few different sentences and see what happens so we can pass in
what are three pets names and we can see that it will recognize that it needs to call the list pets
function with parameters limit equals three we can try another one we can call it with tell me about pet with id
42 and we can see that it calls the show pet by id function with pet id 42
now is a good time to pause and try this out on a few more sample sentences and see what happens
in the example above we showed how you could use the open ai model and choose between different
functions to take now we're going to make that a bit more applied we're going to use that on the two
real functions that we created earlier the weather tool and the wikipedia tool we're going to use the
open ai model to decide which function to invoke and then we're actually going to do the step of invoking
that as well this creates something called routing which is where we're using a language model
to determine which path to take and also the inputs to that path first we're going to create the list
of open ai function specs to use so we're going to call format tool to open ai functions on our two
tools search wikipedia and get current temperature and then we're going to create a model setting temperature
equals zero and binding those functions
let's then call that model on a few sentences so let's call it on what is the weather in sf right now
we can see that it uses the get current temperature tool with arguments for the latitude and longitude
if we call it on what is lane chain we can see that it uses the search wikipedia tool with the query
equals to lane chain we can then take it to the next step and add in a prompt before the language
model call and so we're going to create a super simple chain where there's just this prompt and the
model the prompt is going to be very simple it just says a system message which says you are a helpful
but sassy assistant but we're showing this because when you do need to customize the prompt to make it
more specific to the type of tasks that you're trying to solve this will show you how to set up that pipeline
and now if we invoke the chain on the same inputs we can see that we get back the same responses
so this is good and useful but it's still a little bit annoying because we have this ai message
and we have the content which is null we have the additional quarks which are themselves a dictionary
which then has function calls which is itself a dictionary and so what we want to do
is we're going to convert this into a slightly more usable and workable format
as well let's think about the possible end states for this response from the language model
the two main ones are first when it decides to call a tool and second when it doesn't decide to
call a tool when it doesn't decide to call a tool the main thing that we're interested in
is the value of content here when it does decide to call a tool the main thing that we're interested
in is the tool that it decides to call as well as the input to that tool for the input to that tool
it would be really nice if it wasn't just a string of this json blob but rather parsed out into a
dictionary like we saw done in the tagging and extraction sections we can do this with a new output
parser the open ai functions agent output parser this is going to take in the output and parse it into
a format which has that information first whether it's just a function call or whether it's a response
and then second if it is a function call what is the function that should be called and what is the
input we'll create a chain by combining the prompt above with the model in this new output parser
and then we'll invoke the chain on the same input as before let's now take a look at what result
looks like so if we look at the type of result it is an agent action and that's because what it's
doing is it's going to be calling one of these tools and so if we call result.tool we can now see
exactly what that tool is and if we call result.tool input we have this dictionary of inputs that we want
to pass the tool from there we can do things like pass that tool input into the function itself
so we can pass this in and we can get back the response for the current temperature in sf
what about when there's no tool to call what about when we're just saying hi
if we look at this and we look at the type of this result we can see that we get back in agent finish
if we then look at result.return values which are on all agent finish classes we can see that we get
an output of hello how can i assist you today so we've shown here how depending on the input it could
either be an agent action or an agent finish what exactly is going on under the hood what's happening
is quite simple if a function is called then we take that as an agent action if a function is not called
and it's just a normal response then we represent that as an agent finish we've shown how we can use
a language model to determine what action to take or whether to take an action at all and have this
represented as an agent finish or an agent action the last thing we're going to add in is actually
taking that action if appropriate in order to do that we're going to define a route function this route
function is going to act on the result of the language model and do the corresponding steps so we're going to
check if it's an agent finish and if it is an agent finish we're just going to return the values of
output if it's not an agent finish so if it is an agent action we're going to look up the correct tool
to use and then we're then going to run that tool with the tool input as specified
let's create a new chain which is the same as before except now we're adding in this last step of
this route function we're going to construct a prompt we're going to pass it to the model we're going to
parse that output into an agent finish or an agent action which we're then going to pass into this
route function
let's now call an example where we're asking what the weather is so what is the weather in san
francisco right now if we look at the result we get back the current temperature is 22.9 degrees celsius
let's now do it on an input where we want it to call wikipedia so let's invoke it with what is lane chain if we
look at the result when it's passed back we get back this big blob which is what we got back in the
beginning when we were looking up what lane chain is in the wikipedia tool and then finally let's try
it out on something really simple so if we just do chain invoke and pass in some simple input like just
high we'll just get back a nice simple hello how can i assist you today now is a good time to pause and try this
out on a few different inputs of your choice it's also a good time to try creating new tools and add
those into the list of functions that could be called that wraps up the end of this lesson we've
covered what tools are and shown how we can route between them not only using the language model to
determine what actions to take but then actually adding in a routing step that takes that action
what we'll show in the next lesson is how we can combine this into a loop that continues to iterate
until we reach the agent finish see you there